Okay, okay, Cov, welcome back to the last day of מסכת ברכות.
Masechet Berachot. Today is official דף סד, Daf Samech Dalet, but we
will pick up at the סג עמוד ב, Samech Gimmel Amud Bet,
ten lines from the top, the two dots, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
And so we
are series of related digressions here. It's worth mentioning that the end
of the משנה Mishnah ברכות Berachot did a somewhat of an abrupt
shift from talking about ברכות Berachot and discussing certain practices in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד Baruch
Shem Kevod Malchuto Leolam Va'ed and then ended with a פסוק pasuk
with a discussion about greeting one's friend with God's name, quoting בועז
Boaz and quoting עת לעשות להשם הפרו תורתך, Et La'asot Lashem Heferu
Toratecha, which is quite an interesting way of ending the מסכת. masechet.
What does that exactly have to do with ברכות? Berachot?
It is true the משנה Mishnah said כל חותמי ברכות, Kol Chotmei
Berachot, how they would respond to ברכות, Berachot, but it also spoke
about entering into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and so on. And
I think it's worth thinking about the parallel to the beginning of
the מסכת masechet where it opened with the beginning of שמע Shema
but it also brought us into the world of the מקדש Mikdash
and when the כהנים kohanim eat their תרומה terumah and so on.
And you know one way of understanding what's going on here is
of course it's bringing a world of קדושה kedushah to a post
מקדש Mikdash reality. And that's so much about what the תפילה tefillah
is and what the ברכות berachot are is in sanctifying God and
recognizing God within the natural order of things and so on. So
it's interesting that it both ends also with that sense about entering
in and greeting to the מקדש Mikdash and greeting one's friend with
שם השם, Shem Hashem, bringing God into the day-to-day life. And the
last פסוק pasuk of עת לעשות להשם הפרו תורתך Et La'asot Lashem
Heferu Toratecha in the sense of okay we may maybe it can
be understood along that way, I mean what's the הפרו תורתך Heferu
Toratecha about greeting one's friend with God's name? But nevertheless maybe that's
seen as a little bit of a compromise of the קדושה kedushah
of God's name of using it in such a mundane context. But
no, there was a time in history where that was a very
critical part, it is a critical part of our religious lived reality
and that in a way could be understood about all of מסכת
ברכות. Masechet Berachot. Pretty much all of מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot with
the exception of you know the מצוה mitzvah of שמע Shema let's
say and ברכת התורה, Birchas HaTorah, okay ברכת המזון, Birchas HaMazon, so
not so many, so okay a lot of exceptions. But anyway so
much of מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot is all rabbinic. So much of
our liturgy, the ברכות berachot we say every day, the before we
eat and so on, and nevertheless there's that sense like חבירו בשם
chavero beshem of bringing that קדושה kedushah even if there is a
sort of a little הפרו תורתך heferu toratecha in the sense that
it's not the sort of structure that one has in the תורה,
Torah, it's a realignment of certain senses of how we create קדושה
kedushah but nevertheless how critical that is in our post מקדש Mikdash
reality. So I think it's it's worth thinking about that also yesterday
or two days ago you know I don't think it was hard
to escape the fact that once again we had a whole section
dealing with going to the bathroom. So we had that at the
beginning of the מסכת masechet all this stuff about going to the
bathroom and then right at the end of the מסכת masechet parallelly
all this stuff of going to the bathroom which is a little
bit funny like why are we learning this you know is this
a גמרא? Gemara? But again I mean that idea that even הלכה
halakhah governs there in a sense of bringing קדושה kedushah even to
every single detail of our lives. So I think it's interesting thinking
about the parallel of the way the מסכת masechet opened and closes.
And now we'll turn to also the last section of the גמרא
Gemara which also asks
ourselves like what exactly how is it shaping here the end of
מסכת ברכות. Masechet Berachot. Did you have any insight as to why
I think it worked the Comcast was being more of a barrier?
No I was too late anyway now. Let's take a look now
ten lines from the top on סג עמוד ב Samech Gimmel Amud
Bet from the two dots תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our rabbis taught:
כשנכנסו רבותינו בכרם ביבנה, Keshenichnesu Rabboteinu bekerem beYavneh, when our rabbis went
into the little vineyard of יבנה. Yavneh. This is exactly that moment
of the transition from you know the destruction of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash to reestablishing a new center or establishing a new center
of Judaism in the post מקדש Mikdash world of תורה. Torah. And
יבנה Yavneh becomes the replacement of ירושלים Yerushalayim and it is the
new center and it is the תורה Torah center now of a
post מקדש Mikdash reality of a post מקדש Mikdash Judaism. So when
they entered to יבנה Yavneh היו שם hayu sham רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda ורבי יוסי v'Rabbi Yose ורבי נחמיה v'Rabbi Nechemya ורבי אלעזר בן
שמוע v'Rabbi Elazar ben Shammua ורבי יוסי הגלילי. v'Rabbi Yose HaGlili. So
all these great rabbis were there. Okay. פתחו כולם בכבוד אכסניא. Potchu
kulam bikhvod achsanya. They opened up with honor to the אכסניא, achsanya,
the host. So who exactly is the host? Well we'll take a
look at what they said. This is a very important principle of
פותח בכבוד אכסניא. poteach bikhvod achsanya. Thank you when you open up
to give a דבר תורה dvar Torah or whatever to speak at
a meeting you first thank the host. Okay. So they began with
a thanking of the host. פתח ודרש. Potach vedarash.
And they expounded. פתח יהודה ראש המדברים בכל מקום. Potach Yehuda rosh
hamedabrim bekhol makom. Rabbi Yehuda opened up who always was the first
one had the right to speak first as גמרא Gemara in שבת
Shabbat tells us there was a whole story about him and other
rabbis and he was the one that it was also a type
of a פותח בכבוד אכסניא poteach bikhvod achsanya that Rabbi Yehuda opened
up by praising the Roman government and look how wonderful is the
Roman government that they build roads and you know and and and.
bathhouses and they give us all these wonderful things and other rabbis
opened up with less complimentary things to say about the Roman government
and got in trouble and some didn't say anything anyway so רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda afterwards had the right from the Roman government to
always open every meeting with words of thanks to the host and
פותח אכסניא pote'ach sanya
so we'll see what he says here here it's not about the
Roman government but a very similar scenario is why he got this
right to open up the meetings you seem to
recognize that right even
in the משכן Mishkan yeah well well yes because but they they
were under the Roman government anyway so he opened up ראש המדברים
בכל מקום Rosh hamidabrim b'chol makom the person who always had the
right to open up meetings and here's what he said בכבוד תורה
bichvod Torah so now we're not talking about the about the Roman
government but he opened up with the honor of Torah because their
whole meeting was about convocation was all about Torah ודרש vidarash and
he expounded ומשה יקח את האהל ונטה לו מחוץ למחנה u'Moshe yikach
et haohel v'nata lo michutz lamachaneh Moshe took the tent and he
you know he he put it outside of the camp this was
at you know after the חטא העגל chet haegel and and וקרא
לו אהל מועד v'kara lo ohel mo'ed it says they called it
the tent of meeting and anybody who wanted God would go out
to the camp the tent would go out there so ולא דברים
קל וחומר v'lo d'varim kal vachomer it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer
ומה ארון שלא היה מרוחק אלא שתים עשרה מיל u'mah aron shelo
hayah meruchak ela shtem esrei mil the ארון aron which was only
twelve מיל mil outside of the camp which is about a מיל
mil is about about a מיל mil is about a kilometer so
twelve מיל mil is what whatever that is about nine miles or
so?
Wait didn't the ארון aron in the camp?
No no this is before they built the משכן Mishkan it says
and after the חטא העגל chet haegel it says that Moshe would
take the you know Moshe Moshe Moshe well it doesn't say where
the ארון aron was actually it says Moshe took this וקרא לו
אהל מועד v'kara lo ohel mo'ed it says
I mean you know this was before you had the okay this
so כי תשא Ki Tisa this the חטא העגל chet haegel
Moshe prays to God God says פסל לך שני לוחות אבנים pesol
lcha shnei luchot avanim etc
right so you have the second giving of the of the Torah
and then it says
where was he no that's further excuse me I jumped ahead right
it was before that so anyway right here it was right so
it says right so so so you have the plague after the
עגל egel people die and God says let me you know let
me wipe them all out
okay
right so it says ומשה יקח את האהל u'Moshe yikach et haohel
so everybody's still in big trouble from God ומשה יקח את האהל
ונטה לו מחוץ למחנה הרחק מן המחנה וקרא לו אהל מועד והיה
כל מבקש ה׳ יצא אל אהל מועד אשר מחוץ למחנה u'Moshe yikach
et haohel v'nata lo michutz lamachaneh harchek min hamachaneh v'kara lo ohel
mo'ed v'hayah kol mevakesh Hashem yetzei el ohel mo'ed asher michutz lamachaneh
anybody who wanted God would go to the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed
with Moshe outside of the camp and then it says and that's
where the עמוד הענן amud he'anan would be and וידבר שם ה׳
אל משה v'diber sham Hashem el Moshe and then Moshe prays again
to God and God forgives them and they move on.
I always sensed that it was during the משכן. Mishkan.
No it says מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh I understand that is when
they build the משכן Mishkan this is called אהל מועד ohel mo'ed
if you will with a lowercase א aleph and a lowercase מ
mem this was was a precursor to the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed
this whole point here was that God said רגע אחד אעלה בקרבך
וכיליתיך rega echad eleh bekirbecha v'chiliticha I cannot go in your midst
right so therefore because God could no not be in their midst
the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed was מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh and only
after Moshe prays and God reconciles and forgives the Jewish people then
are they able to build the משכן Mishkan and the אהל מועד
ohel mo'ed and God is able to ושכנתי בתוכם. v'shachanti betocham. So
by itself outside in
the desert no one
is watching no
one's paying
exactly
that's the whole point the whole point is that God cannot be
in their midst so the Moshe takes his tent that becomes the
אהל מועד ohel mo'ed which is outside of the camp and only
after the reconciliation now the command of the משכן Mishkan had already
existed but it had not yet been fulfilled and then you had
the חטא העגל chet haegel right so therefore the משכן Mishkan could
not be that's what God says you know I cannot be בקרבך
bekirbecha so therefore it was מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh and only after
the reconciliation was it brought back inside okay so let's take a
look right here's our well or whatever this sounds like anyway okay
so but what is interesting and maybe was confusing is it mentions
the ארון aron and according to the simple narrative of the Torah
the ארון aron didn't exist yet okay so where exactly where you
know where exactly was the ארון aron is a good question because
the ארון aron was only built after you know he comes down
the second time but they imagine that in this אהל מועד ohel
mo'ed outside the מחנה machaneh was also some ארון aron maybe that's
also where the שברי לוחות shivrei luchot are during this period of
time so let's take a look ומה ארון שלא היה מרוחק אלא
שתים עשרה מיל u'mah aron shelo hayah meruchak ela shtem esrei mil
the ארון aron which was only twelve מיל mil because it was
outside the camp because the size of the Israelite camp was twelve
מיל mil which is about twelve kilometer kilometers so אמרה תורה והיה
כל מבקש ה׳ יצא אהל מועד amrah Torah v'hayah kol mevakesh Hashem
yetzei ohel mo'ed
anybody who wanted to seek out God would leave the would go
to the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed and leave the camp תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim
so that's how far people would go and nevertheless they were called
מבקש ה׳ mevakesh Hashem all they had to do was travel a
lousy twelve מיל mil so תלמידי חכמים שהולכים מעיר לעיר ממדינה למדינה
talmidei chachamim sheholchim me'ir l'ir m'medina l'medina Torah scholars that travel from
city
to city from province to province. city to the next and one
country to the next country ללמוד תורה Torah *lilmod Torah*, קל וחומר
*kal vachomer*, how much more should they be called מבקשי השם *mevakshei
Hashem*? So here it is not so much in the כבוד האכסניא
*kvod hachasanya* but it is in the כבוד *kvod* of תורה Torah.
*Torah* and again one can I think it is important to think
about the symbolism here. The בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* is
destroyed. There is no longer that right ושכנתי בתוכם *veshachanti besocham* that
center of God in the midst that the תורה Torah *Torah* was
describing. What you have now is you have the תורה Torah *Torah*
somewhere on the outskirts at יבנה Yavne, *Yavne*, right? Not where you
had imagined the center would be but outside. And people had to
travel now, they had to travel to come to יבנה Yavne. *Yavne*,
maybe in general the תלמידי חכמים talmidei hachamim, *talmidei chachamim* would travel
from city to city to learn from one another so it was
a different phenomenon. It was similar to the the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash*
is not in our midst, right, but there is a way we
seek out God the same way at the time by משה Moshe
*Moshe* they sought out God when the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* was not
in their midst by leaving the camp. We also do it and
we do it even more than they did in in the time
of משה Moshe *Moshe* and how much more are we called מבקשי
השם *mevakshei Hashem*? So creating that sort of parallel and also very
much giving that very positive weighting to what we are doing. It
should not be seen as גלות *galus*. When you talk about going
מעיר לעיר ממדינה למדינה *me'ir le'ir mimedina limedina* you could call it
a type of a גלות *galus*, right? But here again the idea
is framing this post מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* reality in this positive way.
No, this is what it means to be מבקשי השם *mevakshei Hashem*.
Yes, and I just had this thought. We just finished with בעז
*Boaz* who used who greeted people בשם השם *beshem Hashem* and they
said יברכך השם *yevarechecha Hashem*. So בעז *Boaz* brought the sense of
the sacred into the field where people are working and in the
field, dirty and and all. So what is the חידוש *chiddush* here?
Right, so this is not exactly the same as ברכות Brachot *Berachot*,
but that is something to be thinking about. Here we are doing
a shift from a discussion before of the ברכות berachot *brachot* as
the sort of sanctifying of our reality and שם השם *shem Hashem*
and so on and here the emphasis is a different one. It
is the center of תורה Torah *Torah* replacing the center of מקדש
Mikdash *Mikdash* and I think that that is actually in contrast to
what we have been talking about before. So let's keep that in
mind, that's going to carry us through the end. So let's keep
that in mind. Okay, so now it says like this, okay, וידבר
השם אל משה Moshe פנים אל פנים *vayedaber Hashem el Moshe panim
el panim*, God spoke to משה Moshe. *Moshe*, וידבר, I think, וידבר
השם אל משה פנים אל פנים *vayedaber Hashem el Moshe panim el
panim*. אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא
למשה *amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu leMoshe*, God says to משה *Moshe*,
משה *Moshe*, because this is the end of that you know discussion
about משה *Moshe* being outside the camp. אני ואתה נסביר פנים בהלכה
*Ani ve'atah nasbir panim bahalacha*, you and I let's you know let's
figure out the הלכה *halacha*, let's let's talk about הלכה *halacha*. So
here you have the process of learning הלכה *halacha* and of sort
of classic תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah, *Talmud Torah* as a direct encounter
with God. And again, the power of that in a in a
where תורה Torah *Torah* is replacing מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* as the center.
So as opposed to the the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* being the encounter
of God, the learning of תורה Torah, *Torah* is the encounter of
God. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, others say, כך kach, אמר לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא למשה: כשם שאני הסברתי לך פנים *kach amar lo Hakadosh
Baruch Hu leMoshe: keshem she'ani hisbarti lecha panim*, the same way I
have shown you the face of the תורה Torah *Torah*, I have
explained תורה Torah *Torah* to you, כך kach, אתה הסבר פנים לישראל
והחזיר האוהל למקומו *kach attah hasber panim leYisrael vehechazir haohel limkomo*,
and returned the tent to its place. You have to be amongst
the people, not outside of the people. ושב אל המחנה *Veshav el
hamachaneh*, he would return to the camp, and then it says ומשרתו
יהושע בן נון נער לא ימיש מתוך האוהל *umesharto Yehoshua bin Nun
naar lo yamish mitoch haohel*, יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua bin Nun* would
not move from the tent. אמר רבי אבהו *Amar Rabbi Abbahu*, אמר
לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה *amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu leMoshe*, God
says to משה *Moshe*, עכשיו יאמרו: הרב בכעס ותלמיד בכעס, ישראל מה
תהא עליהם? *achshav yomru: harav bakaas vetalmid bakaas, Yisrael mah tehei aleihem?*.
So so another explanation about why you have to bring the tent
back, not just I did this kindness to you and shared תורה
Torah *Torah* with you, you have to share it with them, but
if we both are outside of the camp then they're going to
feel completely abandoned. So אם אתה מחזיר אוהל למקומו מוטב *im attah
machazir ohel limkomo mutav*, if you return the tent to the place,
good, at least you have to be able to you know show
a in you know a warmth to them and that they're still
cared for. You have to bring the tent back. That would be
good. ואם לאו *Ve'im lav*, and if you refuse to do it,
you feel oh you know if this is the way they're going
to be I'm leaving as well, so then יהושע בן נון תלמידך
משרת תחתיך *Yehoshua bin Nun talmidcha mesharet tachtecha*. If you can't handle
it I'll find somebody else who can and I'll get יהושע *Yehoshua*
to be in the camp with the people. והיינו דכתיב ושב אל
המחנה *Vehainu dichtsiv veshav el hamachaneh*. So he says okay maybe I
better return to the camp. So אמר רבא, אף af, על פי
כן לא יצא דבר לבטלה *amar Rava, af al pi ken lo
yatza davar levatala*, even though that was true, the fact that God
had promised that יהושע *Yehoshua* would be the one to like you
know represent תורה Torah. *Torah* to the people, that did not become
for naught, that was fulfilled, שנאמר: she-ne'emar, משרתו יהושע בן נון נער
לא ימיש מתוך האוהל *shenemar: mesharto Yehoshua bin Nun naar lo yamish
mitoch haohel*, he stayed within the tent and he obviously later took
the position of משה *Moshe*, so in the end he was the
person to present the תורה Torah *Torah* to the people. So the
people cannot remain abandoned. Again, I wonder if this is also there
is a not so hidden message here that God maybe sort of
has a little bit left in the sense that the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* is destroyed, right, the tent is removed outside
of the camp, but the rabbis who clearly see themselves as sort
of as the later incarnation of משה *Moshe*, the replacement of משה
*Moshe* is just because the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? *Beis Hamikdash* is
destroyed we have to you know doesn't mean that you know our
role is still to bring God's תורה Torah to the people. So
משה still has to go back into the camp and bring the
תורה Torah to the people. I think that there's clearly that sort
of text going on here. This is כרם ביבנה, Kerem B'Yavneh, this
is what they're talking about when they are creating this convocation right
after the חורבן, Hurban, which is creates the new the new center,
the center of תורה. Torah, Okay. ועוד פתח רבי יהודה בכבוד תורה.
Ve'od patach Rabbi Yehuda bichvod Torah. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda also opened
in the honor of תורה Torah and ודרש, Ve'darash, הסכת ושמע ישראל.
Hasket u'shema Yisrael.
Be silent and listen Israel. היום הזה
נהיית לעם, Hayom hazeh nihyeita l'am, or or listen up. היום הזה
נהיית
לעם,
Hayom
hazeh
nihyeita l'am, today you have become a people to ה' Hashem your
God. וכי אותו היום ניתנה תורה לישראל? Ve'chi oto hayom nitna Torah
le'Yisrael? Was that day the day that תורה Torah was given to
Israel? This is obviously right near the end of דברים. Devarim. והלא
אותו היום סוף ארבעים שנה היה? Ve'lo oto hayom sof arba'im shana
haya? That was the end of forty years? אלא ללמדך שחביבה תורה
על לומדיה בכל יום ויום כיום שניתנה מהר סיני. Ela lelamedcha shechaviva
Torah al lomedaiha bechol yom vayom keyom shenitna meHar Sinai.
תורה Torah. is as dear to those who learn it like it
was every day given from הר סיני. Har Sinai. Another way the
גמרא Gemara phrases it, בכל יום יהיו בעיניך כחדשים. Bechol yom yihyu
be'eineicha kechadashim. It should be like, you know, אשר אנכי מצוך היום,
Asher anochi metzav'cha hayom, like I command you today, every day it
should be in your eyes as if you were as if it
was given. I tell you, I mentioned before this great line a
friend of mine had once. He said, you know, because there's another
statement but it's also like, you know, ושננתם לבניך, Veshinantam levanecha, שיהיו
דברי תורה משוננים בפיך, Sheyihyu divrei Torah meshunanim beficha,
that the words of תורה Torah should be like sharp and articulate
in your mouth, you know, you shouldn't hesitate, you shouldn't be able
to have instant recall. So he would say to me, he said,
שיהיו מחודדים בפיך, Sheyihyu mechudadim beficha, that I can't do. בכל יום
בעיניך כחדשים, Bechol yom be'eineicha kechadashim, that I'm very good at. So,
anyway, but alright. So anyway, but
the point here is again that learning of תורה, Torah. if it's
done properly, is a re-accepting of, is a new standing at הר
סיני. Har Sinai. And again I think there's a sense of, right,
that's implicit. It's like we re-received it at הר סיני. Har Sinai.
The sense of תורה Torah. as the encounter with God and the,
you know, direct accepting of the תורה Torah, at הר סיני Har
Sinai in the absence of מקדש, Mikdash תורה Torah creates,
is a different and profound way of that of that divine connection
and of קדושה. Kedusha. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב תנחום בריה דרב חייא איש כפר עכו. Amar Rav
Tanchum brei de'Rav Chiya ish Kefar Akko. תדע, Teida, you should know
that how how weighty it is, you know, if you take it
seriously like you received it today from הר סיני. Har Sinai. שאדם
קורא קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית, She'adam korei kariat shema shacharit ve'arvit, a
person every day says קריאת שמע Kariat shema morning and evening. וערב
אחד אינו קורא, Ve'erev echad eino korei,
one day he doesn't read שמע, Shema, he forgot. דומה כמי שלא
קרא קריאת שמע מעולם, Domeh kemi shelo kara kariat shema me'olam, he
feels terrible, says oh my god I missed saying שמע. Shema. I
don't think it means like like his reality is like he's never
done it, but it means experientially he feels terrible that he missed
that one opportunity. Why do you feel so bad? You've said it
a million times over your life. But no, you know, just missing
it once is a terrible thing. I mean, obviously also miss out
the מצוה. Mitzvah. Now again what's important here is the framing of
קריאת שמע Kariat shema as the מצוה Mitzvah of תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah not just as the מצוה Mitzvah of קריאת שמע. Kariat shema.
Interesting also thinking about it in conversation with the beginning of the
מסכת, Masechet, where eventually we got around to the possibility of שמע
Shema connected to תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah. but that's not how it
started. But here again we're taking that even the מצוה Mitzvah of
שמע Shema now becomes that מצוה Mitzvah of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah
So going back to רבקה's Rivka point about how much are we
focusing on sort of ברכות brachos and liturgy as what creates the
קדושה Kedusha of our day, or how much is תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah the center of קדושה. Kedusha. Here it is taking the שמע
Shema and putting it in the column of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
and the missing of the שמע, Shema, you feel terrible, not because
you didn't do the מצוה Mitzvah tonight, but because you lost that
opportunity of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah that one time and that makes
it feel like oh you didn't have that קבלת תורה Kabbalas Torah
from הר סיני Har Sinai that one evening. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues,
okay.
הסכת, Hasket, so now back to דרשה Drasha on הסכת. Hasket. עשו,
Asu, so הסכת, Hasket, like somehow הס Has is like as, the
ה, Hey, the the guttural letter, make a כת, Kat, make a
group. עשו כיתות כיתות ועסקו בתורה. Asu kitot kitot ve'asqu baTorah. Make
little groups and learn תורה. Torah This is the idea of like
learning בחברותא Bechavrusa or learning at least not by yourself. לפי, Lefi,
and also you know the what do you call there דף יומי
Daf Yomi and the you know כרם ביבנה Kerem B'Yavneh was a
big group. לפי שאין התורה נקנית אלא בחבורה. Lefi she'ein haTorah nikneit
ela bechabura. תורה Torah is acquired through in groups. You know, it's
a process of, you know, of conversation, of hearing other people's thoughts,
of getting to the bottom of things. We also know the beginning
of the process of כרם ביבנה Kerem B'Yavneh was taking testimony from
a wide range of people. So there's something very democratic about the
process of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah. and this is the way it's
really acquired. Again if we think that this is still going with
this מקדש Mikdash. contrast, maybe I'm pushing it a little here, but
מקדש Mikdash is anything but democratic. Okay. מקדש Mikdash is you know
כהנים, Kohanim, you can't be a, you know, there's an issue about
about בעלי מומים, Ba'alei mumim, I mean for the כהנים Kohanim themselves,
טומאה, Tum'ah, there's all these things that keep people outside. And most
fundamentally קרבנות Korbanot are private with the one exception of like קרבן
פסח. Korban pesach. I mean with the קרבן תמיד Korban tamid which
is the entire collective. But תורה is very different. תורה is democratic,
small groups, people getting together. At the house of רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. Okay, yeah.
Fine, okay. That's true. Okay, so where are we?
ר' יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Yose bar Hanina, this is like ר'
יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Yose bar Hanina, דאמר ר' יוסי בר חנינא,
d'amar Rabbi Yose bar Hanina, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by
the
פסוק, pasuk, חרב אל הבדים ונואלו? Herev el ha-baddim ve-noalu? A sword
to the בדים, baddim, which is a hard word to understand in
that context, it could mean—I forget how they translate it there anyway—and
they will be foolish. So who are the בדים? baddim? It says,
חרב אל שונאיהם של תלמידי חכמים, Herev el soneihem shel talmidei hachamim,
a sword figuratively against those who hate the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei hachamim
which is a euphemism for the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim when you
don't want to say something
bad, שיושבים בד בבד ועוסקים בתורה, she-yoshvim bad be-vad ve-oskim ba-Torah, if
they sit alone, a בד, bad, לבד, levad, alone, then they're being—then
it's a terrible thing, like a sword should be raised against them.
ולא עוד, V'lo od, not only is it a bad thing, אלא
שמיטפשין, ela she-mitapshin, they'll think, "Oh, yeah, fine, I'm not being so
nice, I'm not being so democratic, but I learn better by myself."
No, you become stupid that way. כתיב הכא, Ktiv hacha, ונואלו, ve-noalu,
be foolish, וכתיב התם, u-chtiv hatam, אשר נואלנו, asher noalnu,
that we have been foolish. ולא עוד, Ve-lo od, and not only
are you foolish, אלא שחוטאים, ela she-chotim, you sin, שנאמר, She-ne'emar, ואשר
נואלנו ואשר חטאנו. va-asher noalnu ve-asher chatanu.
Okay, so it's a very bad thing, and not only that, it
doesn't even help with your learning, your learning grows when you learn
with other people.
What's the literal translation of the verse?
הבדים? Ha-baddim? I don't know. Take a look. There are different translations.
Here they say "alone" and then ונואלו ve-noalu for "be foolish".
Anyway, there are different translations. איבעית אימא מהכא, Iba'it eima me-hacha, if
you want from here. נואלו שרי צוען, Noalu sarei tzo'an,
the officers of Tzo'an have been foolish. Okay, so another point where
obviously נואלו noalu is a bad thing. דבר אחר, Davar acher, הסכת,
Hasket, so that's one הסכת, Hasket, learning groups. הסכת ושמע ישראל, Hasket
u-shma Yisrael, כתתו עצמכם על דברי תורה. katetu atzmechem al divrei Torah.
So הס, Has, עשו כת, asu kat, like a group, but לכתת
l'chatet means like to grind. Grind yourself over the learning of Torah.
דאמר ריש לקיש, De-amar Resh Lakish, דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Resh Lakish,
מניין שדברי תורה מתקיימין אלא במי שממית עצמו עליה? minayin she-divrei Torah
mitkaymin ela be-mi she-memit atzmo aleiha? How do you know Torah is
only sustained by somebody who is willing to, like, kill himself for
it, figuratively not literally? שנאמר, shenemar: זאת התורה
אדם כי ימות באוהל, zot ha-Torah adam ki yamut be-ohel, if a
person dies in the tent, they're willing to die in the tent
of Torah, that sense of self-sacrifice.
Now, of course, this is figurative, but one remembers a day or
two ago the דרשה drasha with רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right, who
said, how could you, you know, that he'd rather give up his
life for learning Torah than stop learning Torah. So there's also, you
know, there's also times in which it had a literal fulfillment like
that story over there. Anyway, דבר אחר, davar acher, so that is
the sense of self-sacrifice it requires. הסכת ושמע ישראל, Hasketu u-shma Yisrael,
הס ואחר כתת. Has ve-achar koteitz.
First silence, listen, then you can grind, then you can analyze. So
don't start asking questions right away, first pay attention, listen, absorb information,
then you can start analyzing and asking. כדי רבא, Ke-de-Rava, דאמר רבא,
de-amar Rava, לעולם ילמד אדם תורה ואחר כך יהגה. l'olam yilmad adam
Torah ve-achar kach yehgeh. First you should learn Torah
and afterward you should think about it, then you should, like, analyze
it, okay? So first, like, you know, absorb information, and we're going
to repeat into that theme in a minute. This is, of course,
particularly true in a time where it was תורה שבעל פה Torah
she-ba'al peh and you didn't have the access to the book, so
you had to absorb an enormous amount of information orally and memorize
it so that you would have the raw material to then analyze.
Okay. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, Amrei devei Rabbi Yannai, מאי דכתיב, mai
de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse, כי מיץ חלב יוציא חמאה, Ki
mitz chalav yotzi chemah,
the juice of milk will produce butter, ומיץ אף יוציא דם, u-mitz
af yotzi dam, and the liquid of—the squeezing of the nose will
produce blood, ומיץ אפים יוציא ריב, u-mitz apayim yotzi riv, and the
squeezing of the face or of the anger will bring out fight,
dispute.
במי אתה מוצא חמאה של תורה? Bimi atah motzei chemah shel Torah?
Where do you find the butter, the choice part of Torah? במי
שמקיא חלב שינק משדי אמו עליה. Bi-mi she-maki chalav she-yanak mi-shadei imo
aleiha. A person who is willing to so much self-sacrifice that they
spit out even the milk that they nursed from their mother's breast.
So they totally, like, you know, give it their blood and sweat
and tears, we would say. Yes. ומיץ אף יוציא דם, U-mitz af
yotzi dam, כל תלמיד שכועס עליו רבו פעם ראשונה ושותק. kol talmid
she-ko'es alav rabbo pa'am rishonah ve-shoteik. So what does this mean about
blood coming out? Anybody—a student whose teacher gets angry at him the
first time and is silent, so then זוכה להבחין בין דם טמא
לדם טהור. zocheh lehavchin bein dam tamei le-dam tahor.
So if it's somehow מיץ, mitz, I don't know how they get
מיץ, mitz, but אף, af אף af, is anger. So somehow you
get the juice of the anger, the distillation of the anger, you
absorb it, you don't respond, then יוציא דם, yotzi dam, then you
are able
to—out from you will come rulings relating to blood. Pure blood and
tamei blood, which is, you know, you'll get to greatness in Torah.
ומיץ אפים יוציא ריב,
U-mitz apayim
yotzi
riv, כל תלמיד
שכועס עליו רבו פעם ראשונה ושניה ושותק.
kol
talmid she-ko'es
alav rabbo pa'am rishonah u-shniyah ve-shoteik.
So what's this about the distillation of the anger? So it's not
just it's אפים, apayim, it's not אף, af אף is one, אפים
apayim is plural, so he gets angry at you twice ושניה u-shniyah
and you still don't respond. You internalize it and whatever, you become
humble, you commit yourself more. זוכה להבחין בין דיני ממונות לדיני נפשות.
zocher le-havchin bein dinei mamonot le-dinei nefashot. Then יוציא ריב yotzi riv
is able to דין, din, deal between fights, between disputes, monetary disputes
and even capital cases, which requires a great level of Torah knowledge.
It's now we turn to the Mishnah. רבי ישמעאל אומר הרוצה שיחכים
יעסוק בדיני ממונות, Rabbi Yishmael omer harotze she-yitchakem ya-asok b'dinei mamonot, if
somebody wants to be wise, he should spend time on monetary laws,
שאין לך מקצוע בתורה יותר מהן, she-ein lecha miktzoa ba-Torah yoser mehen,
you have no greater profession of Torah, no greater area of Torah
to devote yourself to more than civil disputes, שהן כמעיין הנובע, she-hen
k'mayan hanove'a, they are like a wellspring that flows. It requires a
tremendous amount, requires a tremendous amount of depth and knowledge. אמר רבי
יהושע בן לחמני, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Lachmani, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv,
what's meant by the pasuk, אם נבלת בהתנשא, im navalta behitnasei,
if you have somehow degraded yourself in lifting yourself up, ואם זמות,
v'im zamota, and if you have made plans or deceit, יד לפה,
yad lapeh, your hand should be to your mouth. So how are
we going to darshan that? כל המנבל עצמו על דברי תורה, kol
hamenabel atzmo al divrei Torah, if you are willing to degrade yourself
over Torah, meaning that
you accept when your Rebbe yells at you or you accept criticism,
or Rashi says you're willing to ask questions that maybe make yourself
look foolish, you don't stand on your pride, you sacrifice even your
own pride for the sake of Torah, סופו להתנשא, sofo lehitnasei, in
the end you will be lifted up, you'll be a great Torah
sage. ואם זמם v'im zamam or ואם זמות v'im zamota maybe should
be, and if you, יד לפה, yad lapeh, and if you put
a seal on your mouth, let me just see Rashi explains that
I think one minute. ואם
שמת פיך משל לשון זמם, v'im samta picha mashal lashon zamam, right,
and if you put a seal on your mouth,
then יד לפה, yad lapeh, then you'll have to put your own
hand over your mouth. If you don't ask questions to your Rebbe,
then you'll have to put your own hand over your mouth, you
won't be able to answer when other people ask you. So here
clearly there's a strong emphasis about self-sacrifice not only in time and
effort but also just in terms of pride, the way of giving
oneself over for the sake of תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah I do
wonder again, and
maybe I'm pushing this a little bit, but I do wonder if
we see this somewhat in conversation with
בית המקדש. One of the powers of the idea of קרבנות, korbanot,
I mean we obviously
nowadays have a hard time relating to the idea of קרבנות, korbanot,
but obviously a clear sense of the power of it is you're
giving over of something that is most dear to you.
Either just simply, even non-metaphorically,
here you are, you work the whole year to raise these sheep
and these cows and this grain and all this stuff, that was
their primary product and they give it like ביכורים, bikurim, and you
give this thing that represents all of your efforts. And also then
symbolically, the animal is life and it could be a symbolic way
of almost giving of oneself over to God. So here in this
context about Torah after describing how the Torah basically is like the
encountering of God at אהל מועד Ohel Moed and the receiving of
the Torah at הר סיני, Har Sinai, it's this profound relationship to
God even without מקדש, you have these metaphors here which are very
much about self-sacrifice and giving up of your blood, your sweat, your
tears, and the sacrifice of your pride and all these types of
things in the process of learning Torah. Okay, so that was the
opening דרשות. drashot. Now we move on, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
פתח רבי יוסי בכבוד אכסניא. Patach Rabbi Yossi bichvod achsanya.
Now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi turned from, I'm sorry, דוד בן נחמני.
David ben Nachmani. I'm sorry, I skipped. Turned to רבי נחמיה בכבוד
אכסניא. Rabbi Nechemia bichvod achsanya. That was בכבוד תורה, bichvod Torah, because
it was a Torah convocation. But now we have to get back
to the idea you're supposed to open with the honoring the host.
So רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia opened with כבוד אכסניא kvod achsanya and
דרש. darash. מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, ויאמר שאול אל
הקיני, vayomer Shaul el ha-Keini, Saul said to the Keini, לכו סורו
רדו מתוך עמלקי, lechu suru redu mitoch Amaleki, go, remove yourselves from
the Amalekites, פן אוסיפך עמו, pen osifcha imo, lest I wipe you
out with them, ואתה עשית חסד עם כל בני ישראל, v'ata asita
chesed im kol Bnei Yisrael, you did kindness with all the children
of Israel, right when they came out of מצרים. Mitzrayim. יתרו, Yisro,
your forefather,
welcomed משה and so on. So והלא דברים קל וחומר v'halo devarim
kal v'chomer from this, ומה יתרו שלא קירב את משה אלא לכבוד
עצמו, u'mah Yisro shelo kirev es Moshe ela lichvod atzmo, Yisro only
welcomed Moshe for his own honor, I don't know how we know
that, but that's what we're saying, that he did it because, oh
my God, here's my son-in-law, a big shot, I better go out
and welcome him, it looks good for me. So that's how we're
reading it. כך, and nevertheless they were given, his descendants were given
this tremendous honor or this accommodation that they were protected while in
this fight against עמלק. Amalek. המארח תלמיד חכם בתוך ביתו, hamareiach talmid
chacham betoch beito,
somebody who hosts Torah scholars in their house, ומאכילו ומשקהו, u'machilo u'mashkeihu,
and feeds him and gives him drink, ומהנהו מנכסיו, u'mehanehu minchasav, and
allows him to benefit from his property, על אחת כמה וכמה, al
achas kama v'chama,
how much more will that person be rewarded. Now normally when you
see a statement like this, you normally think that it's sort of
direct tries to tell people this is what you should do guys,
if you have Torah scholars that are, and if especially we learned.
before about people moving from place to place, if you're getting together,
you know, so if some תלמיד חכם talmid chacham Torah scholar comes
your way, you should welcome them into your house and feed them
and have them stay by you, and so on. And obviously we
know, you know, for hundreds of years, you know, till very, I
know, in Europe even, what, a hundred years ago or so, you
know, that was very common, that people would come from other towns
to learn תורה, and the בעלי בתים ba'alei batim of the town,
you know, would be expected to open up their homes and try
to provide for them. You know their עסן טאג, Essen Tag, right,
eating a day, where they would go to a different person's home
each day. It wasn't always so much that they got the most
comfortable accommodations, but at least they were accommodated. So normally you hear
a statement like this and you think it's trying to encourage people
to practice this behavior, which certainly it could be, but in this
context it's פתח בכבוד אכסניא, pasach bichvod achsanya, it's thanking, it's—this is
already presumably what's already happened. We've already gathered this convocation of sages
at יבנה, Yavneh people are putting them up, people are hosting them.
So we are giving the thanks to people about how much reward
they will get
for hosting the sages that are here in יבנה. And it wasn't
just for a few days, it wasn't a conference for a few
days, you know, they stayed there for a long time and people
presumably were doing that on an ongoing basis. Okay, so now we're
going to see a similar statement by רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. פתח
רבי יוסי בכבוד אכסניא, pasach Rabbi Yosi bichvod achsanya, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi opened with the honor of the host, ודרש: vidarash: לא תתעב
אדומי כי אחיך הוא, lo tisa'ev Adomi ki achicha hu, do not
despise the Edomite because he is your brother; לא תתעב מצרי כי
גר היית בארצו, lo tisa'ev Mitzri ki ger hayita be'artzo, do not
despise the Egyptian because
you were a sojourner in his land. והלא דברים קל וחומר: vihalo
devarim kal vachomer: ומה מצרים מצריים שלא קירבו את ישראל אלא לצורך
עצמם, uma Mitzrayim Mitzriyim shelo kirevu es Yisrael ela litzorech atzmam, the
Egyptians only brought us close for their own interests, שנאמר: shenemar, ואם
ידעת ויש בם אנשי חיל ושמתם שרי מקנה על אשר לי, ve'im
yadata veyesh bam anshei chayil vesamtam sarei mikneh al asher li, Pharaoh
said, if there's any that can be my officers, you know, heads
of my shepherds, let me know about it. So again, just because
he wanted some benefit didn't mean that was his whole motivation, but
nevertheless that's how we're framing it. כך, and nevertheless look at this,
they got—that they were given this protection that we can't go to
war against them. המארח תלמיד חכם בתוך ביתו מאכילו ומשקהו ומהנהו מנכסיו
על אחת כמה וכמה, hame'are'ach talmid chacham betoch beito ma'achilo umashkehu umehanehu
minechasav al achas kama vechama, somebody who hosts Torah sages in his
house, feeds him, and gives him drink and allows him to benefit
from his property, how much more will they be rewarded. Now so
far the reward is just that they won't be wiped out, in
the two examples. Now we're going to go to a little bit
more, right, not עמלק Amalek or מצרי. Mitzri. Let's go to a
little bit more of a positive example. פתח רבי אלעזר בנו של
רבי יוסי הגלילי בכבוד אכסניא. pasach Rabbi Elazar beno shel Rabbi Yosi
haGlili bichvod achsanya. So now he opened up with the honor of
the host, ודרש, vidarash, and he made a drasha: ויברך ה׳ את
עובד אדום בעבור ארון האלהים, vayivarech Hashem es Oved Edom ba'avur aron
haElokim,
God blessed עובד אדום Oved Edom because of the ארון aron of
God that was in his house. You remember this is what was
stored, right, prior to it being brought up to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
and he was a non-Jew. והלא דברים קל וחומר: vihalo devarim kal
vachomer: ומה ארון שלא אכל ושתה אלא כיבד וריבץ לפניו, uma aron
shelo achal vishasa ela kibed veribetz lefanav, what do you have to
do for the ארון? aron? He didn't have to feed it, he
didn't have to drink it, didn't have to change the mattress, right,
or whatever, all you had to do was like sweep and keep
the room clean, and that's what he did for the ארון. aron.
וכך, vikach, and look how he was rewarded, and he was very
rewarded, in the פסוקים pesukim it's clear he was like very, very
blessed. המארח תלמיד חכם בתוך ביתו מאכילו ומשקהו ומהנהו מנכסיו על אחת
כמה וכמה, hame'are'ach talmid chacham betoch beito ma'achilo umashkehu umehanehu minechasav al
achas kama vechama, how much more so somebody who hosts a Torah
sage. What I like about this is that this actually ties together
the two themes. It's both showing the reward you get for hosting
the Torah sage, for כבוד אכסניא, kvod achsanya, and we have again
Torah identified here with the ארון. aron. So you know, the honor
shown to the ארון, aron, you get even more reward when you
show honor to a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and you host a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham even more than the ארון. aron. So again
this sense of the Torah and תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah, replacing the
center of the מקדש. Now, מהי ברכה שבירכו, mahi bracha shebercho, what
was the blessing that he was blessed with? אמר רב יהודה בר
זבידא: amar Rav Yehuda bar Zvida: זו חמות ושמונה כלותיה, zu chamot
ushmona kaloteha, this is חמות Chamot which is his wife and her
eight daughters-in-law, שילדו ששה ששה בבטן אחת sheyaldu shisha shisha bebeten achat
of עובד אדום, Oved Edom, this non-Jew who the ארון aron was
being kept in his house, שילדו ששה ששה בכרס אחת, sheyaldu shisha
shisha becheres achat,
each one of them had six—had
sextuplets—sextuplets—what do you call it? Sextuplets—sextet—sextuplets. Is that here in the תנ״ך?
Tanach? No, I don't think so. Yeah, yeah, I believe so. שנאמר,
she'ne'emar okay: פעולתי השמיני, Pe'ulati hashmini, so פעולתי Pe'ulati was the name
of his eighth son of עובד, Oved, וכתיב כי ברכו אלוהים, uchisiv
ki beracho Elokim, God blessed him. כל אלה מבני עובד אדום המה,
kol eleh mivnei Oved Edom hemah, all of these were the children
of עובד אדום, Oved Edom, so he had eight sons, so that
means eight daughters-in-law and his wife is
nine, ובניהם ואחיהם איש חיל בכח לעבודה ששים ושנים לעובד אדום, uvneihem
va'acheihem ish chayil beko'ach la'avoda shishim ushnayim le'Oved Edom, sixty-two, he
had sixty-two, he presumably sixty-two kids and grandkids, so he had sixty-two,
plus he had, so how do you work it out? So there
are—so you figure if there are six—his six daughters-in-law and his wife
is nine and each one has six kids, that's fifty-four plus his
own eight sons, so there you get sixty-two. Okay. Yes.
The structure of this עמוד amud is very similar to the structure
of a lot of the מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah where you have
the פתיחה, psicha, yeah, and then a—and then a— The structure of
this עמוד amud is very similar to the
structure of a lot of מדרש רבה, Midrash Rabbah, where you have
the פתיחה, pesichah, and then a פסוק pasuk and then a דרש
drash on the פסוק. pasuk. That's a good point. That's important. What?
Yeah, the פתח, petach, the פתח petach also by the מדרש רבה.
Midrash Rabbah. That's a good point.
We'll also have to see by the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael though
in מצרים, Mitzrayim, right?
So yeah, that's a different דרשה, drasha, right? שישה בכרס אחד.
shishah bikeres echad. Right.
Okay, so now, okay,
so that's the end of opening up and as I said, very
important both about those אחסניא achsanya that are hosting the Torah sages
for this כנפי יבנה, Kanaf Yeivneh, but also very important about post-Mikdash
and about Torah taking its place. Okay, now it says אמר רבי
אבין הלוי, Amar Rabbi Avin HaLevi, the end of these דרשה drasha
will also end with an emphasis on Torah. כל הדוחק את השעה
שעה דוחקתו. kol hadochek es hashaah shaah dochakto.
Anybody that pushes the hour, the hour pushes him away, meaning if
you try to rush things then you lose what status you would
have got, you lose the honor you would have received. וכל הנדחה
מפני שעה שעה נדחית מפניו. v'chol hanidcheh mipnei shaah shaah nidcheis mipanav.
Anybody that's willing to allow himself to be pushed away because of
the needs of the hour,
in the end, the hour will be pushed away for his needs,
he will raise to greatness, rise to greatness. מדרבה ורב יוסף. mi-de-Rabbah
v'Rav Yosef. We can learn this from Rabbah and Rav Yosef. דרב
יוסף סיני ורבה עוקר הרים. de-Rav Yosef Sinai v'Rabbah Okeir Harim. Okay,
Rav Yosef was like הר סיני, Har Sinai, he knew all of
the Torah, but he knew it like מסורה, mesorah, he knew it,
he knew the facts.
Rabbah was lifted up the mountain, he didn't just receive it from
Har Sinai, he was able to uproot the mountains, to grind the
mountains, he was able to analyze and use critical
analysis of the way he's looking at what he had received. So
that's like the גמרא Gemara before about first listening and then analyzing.
אצטריכו ליה שעתא. itztrichu leh shaata. Now notice about the שעה, shaah,
the hour was needed. Somebody was needed to be
a ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. שדרו להתם. shadru lehasam. They sent to
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. סיני ועוקר הרים איזה מהם קודם. Sinai v'okeir
harim eizeh mehem kodem. If you have one person who's a סיני
Sinai like Har Sinai and the other who's an uprooter of mountains,
which one comes first? Now again, comes first for what purposes? Like
who is
greater? But here whenever they ask these questions like who's better, the
question is is it like an absolute or within a particular
context? Maybe here the question is who should be the ראש ישיבה.
Rosh Yeshiva. So let's see what they answer. שלחו להו, shalchu lehu,
they sent back to them: סיני קודם, Sinai kodem, Sinai comes first,
שהכל צריכין למרי חטיא. shehakol tzerichin lemarei chtaya. Everybody needs the grinder
of wheat. Now, what it means is that you can't get anywhere
like the גמרא Gemara said before until you have the facts. You
need to have all of the knowledge and all of the מסורה
mesorah and then you can analyze it. If somebody doesn't have, so
that person is the most fundamental and the basis for the Torah
learning, that person has to come first. It's interesting that the example
of the person who owns the wheat, the wheat has to be
ground, so but that's the point, but you can't grind the wheat
and make flour until you buy the wheat. So he comes first
and therefore he should be the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, at least
for that.
Doesn't necessarily mean that that's where any individual should expend their energy,
that's like a separate question, but here's the question about who needs
to be the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva.
אפילו הכי, afilu hachi, and even so that Rav Yosef was made
the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, לא קביל עליה רב יוסף, lo kabil
aleih Rav Yosef, Rav Yosef refused to accept the honor. דאמרי ליה
כלדאי. d'amri leh Kalda'ei. Now this is fascinating because the כלדאי, Kalda'ei,
certain magicians had told him or seers had told him, מלוך תרתין
שנין, maloch tartin shnin, you'll only be king, you'll only be like
the leader for two years and then you'll die. So he figured
maybe I will postpone being leader. So Rabbah, so therefore what happened?
So it's interesting that he listened to them. So מלך רבה עשרין
ותרתין שנין. malach Rabbah esrin v'sartin shnin. So
Rabbah was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva for twenty-two years. ולבסוף מלך
רב יוסף תרתין שנין ופלגא. u'levasof malach Rav Yosef tartin shnin u'palga.
And then he was the head for two and a half years,
he was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva for two and a half
years and then he died. So it was why? So you see
that he allowed himself to step aside and in the end he
got the honor that was coming to him. Now the only reason
he let himself step aside is he didn't want this prediction to
come true. But nevertheless you see if you step aside, in the
end the honor will come to you.
I can't help but see the irony over here that Rav Yosef
was the סיני Sinai and knew all the facts and then getting
sick later and then forgetting.
That's
interesting, but that's a good point too. It's a very good point
too that Rav Yosef got sick and he forgot his Torah, yeah.
That's a very good point. You wonder when that happened because he
was only ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva for two and a half years
and then he died.
Maybe he didn't die
after—רש״י Rashi says as if he died.
Oh yeah,
maybe. That's a good point. But that's a very good point that
Rav Yosef did forget his Torah, that's right. Okay, so וכל הנך
שני דמלך רבה, v'chol hanach shnei d'malach Rabbah, and not only that,
all those years that Rabbah was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva for
those twenty-two years, אפילו אומנא לביתי לא קרא. afilu umna leveiti lo
kara. Rav Yosef did not want to show any demonstration of authority
and he didn't even have a doctor, literally a bloodletter pay a
house call. He didn't want anybody to show him honor because that
he felt would be somehow undermining Rabbah's status. Okay, so here we
get go again to this idea about different forms of תלמוד תורה,
Talmud Torah. סיני Sinai and עוקר הרים. Okeir Harim. ואמר רבי אבין,
V'amar Rabbi Avin, so since
Rabbi Avin said that previous statement about דוחק את השעה, dochek es
hashaah, we end with a few statements of his. הלוי, HaLevi, מאי
דכתיב יענך ה׳ ביום צרה. mai d'chsiv yaancha Hashem b'yom tzarah. God
will answer you at a time of affliction. ישגבך שם אלהי יעקב,
yesagvecha shem elohei Yaakov,
the God of Jacob will protect you. ולא, V'lo, so it says
אלהי יעקב Elohei Yaakov ולא אלהי אברהם ויצחק? v'lo Elohei Avraham v'Yitzchak?
Why the God of Jacob? How about the God of Abraham and
Isaac? So מכאן לבעל הקורה שיכנס בעוביה של קורה mikan l'ba'al hakora
sheyikanes b'ovya shel kora
that the owner of the beam is the one that should go
under the sort of thickness of the beam. If it's your you
know so therefore if it's you know your you're building a house
it's your beam you're the one that has to you know if
you're if you're the one responsible you have to put yourself under
the beam and take the full brunt weight of the responsibility so
how's that relevant here? So the way רש״י Rashi explains it is
that יעקב Yaakov who was the one that raised the twelve sons
and from him really comes all of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, you
know אברהם ויצחק Avraham v'Yitzchak not all their sons were you know
were
led into בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. יעקב Yaakov raised had to raise
a big huge family so he's the one that he has to
take the full responsibility of the family and he is the one
that you know so it's the God of יעקב Yaakov that will
come to our protection because the responsibility fully lays on him. ואמר
רבי אבין הלוי V'amar Rabbi Avin HaLevi wow he has to pray
for them right. ואמר רבי אבין הלוי כל הנהנה מסעודה שתלמיד חכם
שרוי בתוכה V'amar Rabbi Avin HaLevi kol haneheneh mis'udah she'talmid chacham sharuy
b'tochah back to back to תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim, and
hosting them. Anybody who benefits from a meal that a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham is present at, so even if you're not hosting him
but you're present at you're indeed you're also partaking of the same
meal, כאילו נהנה מזיו השכינה k'ilu neheneh miziv hashchinah and again notice
the connection to right the presence of God זיו השכינה ziv hashchinah
this again substitute for the בית המקדש. What was one of the
other things they did in the בית המקדש? You brought קרבנות korbanot
and you ate them. So here we had before you know sacrificing
of yourself and now benefiting and eating from the meals that the
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham are present in שנאמר ויבא אהרן וכל זקני
ישראל לאכל לחם עם חתן משה לפני האלהים shenemar vayavo Aharon v'chol
ziknei Yisrael le'echol lechem im choten Moshe lifnei HaElohim they came to
eat bread with Moses' father-in-law before God. וכי לפני אלהים אכלו? V'chi
lifnei Elohim achlu? Did they eat before God? ולא לפני משה אכלו?
V'lo lifnei Moshe achlu? Before Moses? אלא לומר לך כל הנהנה מסעודה
שתלמיד חכם שרוי בתוכה Ella lomar lach kol haneheneh mis'udah she'talmid chacham
sharuy b'tochah
when you eat from the meal that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
is present at כאילו נהנה מזיו השכינה k'ilu neheneh miziv hashchinah like
benefiting from the glory of the shining glory of God's presence.
I know what does he miss in the פסוק? pasuk?
I know I know חתן משה. choten Moshe. Okay ואמר רבי אבין.
v'amar Rabbi Avin.
How is he not a תלמיד חכם?
talmid chacham? No well משה is a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
in this way of לאכל לחם
עם חתן משה.
le'echol
lechem im choten Moshe. I know that's what Michael just said. They
sort of bracket the חתן משה choten Moshe and they focus on
the משה. Not exactly פשט. pshat. ואמר רבי אבין הלוי V'amar Rabbi
Avin HaLevi הנפטר מחברו haniftar mechavero if you're leaving your friend אל
יאמר לו לך בשלום al yomar lo lech b'shalom go with peace
אלא לך לשלום ela lech l'shalom go towards peace. שהרי יתרו Sheharei
Yitro since since we've been discussing יתרו Yitro and it's also the
same רבי אבין הלוי Rabbi Avin HaLevi שהרי יתרו שאמר לו למשה
לך לשלום sheharei Yitro she'amar lo l'Moshe lech l'shalom go to peace
עלה והצליח alah v'hitzliach was successful. דוד שאמר לו לאבשלום לך בשלום
David she'amar lo l'Avshalom lech b'shalom go with peace הלך ונתלה halach
v'nitlah he went and he was he was hanged at by the
tree. Presumably the difference is that we never achieve perfection so your
life is always working towards peace towards something but if you're with
peace the only way in which you're with you've achieved peace is
when you're dead otherwise you're always working towards achieving something achieving it.
ואמר רבי אבין הלוי V'amar Rabbi Avin HaLevi הנפטר מן המת haniftar
min hamet very similar statement if you leave a dead body אל
יאמר לו לך לשלום al yomar lo lech l'shalom it's reverse don't
say to the מת met go towards peace אלא לך בשלום ela
lech b'shalom with peace שנאמר ואתה תבוא אל אבותיך בשלום. shenemar v'atah
tavo el avotecha b'shalom. Okay. Now אמר רבי לוי בר חייא amar
Rabbi Levi bar Chiya היוצא מבית הכנסת hayotze mibheit haknesset so I've
been sort of arguing that the whole דף daf today is about
sort of showing תורה as the replacement center of קדושה kedushah after
the מקדש but in a way that's different than saying the ברכות
brachos and the liturgy is what creates קדושה kedushah in our lives
like Boaz in the field says Riskas said. So with that in
mind look at the look at the this almost last statement of
the מסכת. masechet. אמר רבי לוי ברבי חייא Amar Rabbi Levi berabbi
Chiya היוצא מבית הכנסת ונכנס לבית המדרש hayotze mibheit haknesset v'nichnas l'beit
hamidrash if one leaves the synagogue and goes into the study hall
meaning after you דאוונד davened you go into the study hall ועוסק
בתורה v'osek baTorah
and involve himself in תורה זוכה ומקבל פני שכינה zoche u'mekabel pnei
Shchinah merits to receive the presence the face of the divine presence
שנאמר ילכו מחיל אל חיל יראה אל אלהים בציון shenemar yelchu m'chayil
el chayil yera'eh el Elohim b'Tziyon they go from strength to strength
you will see God in Zion. Now notice obviously we're not saying
that you know דאוונינג davening is not important but it seems very
clear the whole point is that that is the first step. You
start your day with דאוונינג. davening. But what are you then supposed
to do? You go to a בית מדרש beit midrash which is
the other center and you devote ועוסק בתורה v'osek baTorah you devote
yourself in תורה. Then it's like you have this encounter with God
not through דאוונינג. davening. דאוונינג Davening you don't פני שכינה. pnei Shchinah.
In the בית מדרש beit midrash when you're learning תורה that's when
יראה אל אלהים בציון. yera'eh el Elohim b'Tziyon. And this is the
new ציון Tziyon right? The new ציון Tziyon is now the the
בית מדרש beit midrash of the learning of תורה. So it ties
in the whole תפילה tefillah experience but ultimately the next the final
stage is the תלמוד תורה. And we'll end with אמר רבי חייא
בר אשי אמר רב amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav תלמידי
חכמים אין להם מנוחה talmidei chachamim ein lahem menuchah Torah sages have
no peace לא בעולם הזה ולא בעולם הבא lo ba'olam hazeh v'lo
ba'olam haba not in this world or the next world. They're always
you know
growing or grappling and struggling in their religious growth שנאמר ילכו מחיל
אל חיל יראה אל אלהים בציון. shenemar yelchu m'chayil el chayil yera'eh
el Elohim b'Tziyon. So this is also a process of growth. growth
is the process of learning תורה. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא,
Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Chanina, תלמידי חכמים מרבים שלום בעולם. talmidei
chachamim marbim shalom ba'olam. People should know this, שנאמר וכל בנייך למודי
השם ורב שלום בנייך. vechol banayich limudei Hashem verav shalom banayich. They
create peace in the world as it says all of your children
are learned of God and much peace from your children, אל תקרי
בנייך al tikrei banayich your children אלא בונייך ella bonayich
those that build you, so again which sort of begs the question
why does בונייך bonayich mean תלמידי חכמים, but okay. שלום רב לאוהבי
תורתך ואין למו מכשול, Shalom rav le'ohavei toratecha ve'ein lamo michshol, יהי
שלום בחילך, yehi shalom becheilech, שלום shalom three times, a lot of
nice peace related to תורה, שלווה בארמנותייך, shalva be'armenotayich, למען אחי ורעי
אדברה נא שלום בך, lema'an achai vere'ai adabra na shalom bach, למען
בית השם אלוקינו אבקשה טוב לך, lema'an beit Hashem Elokeinu avaksha tov
lach, השם עוז לעמו ייתן השם יברך את עמו בשלום. Hashem oz
le'amo yiten Hashem yevarech et amo bashalom. Exactly.
So obviously ending בשלום beshalom which is a beautiful way of ending
this right and ברכות end with שלום, shalom, ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim
ends with שלום, shalom, כמה מברכות kama mibrachos are בשלום, beshalom, so
we end שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei בשלום, beshalom, so we end the
מסכת masechet about תפילה tefilla בשלום, beshalom,
but again with all of this שלום שלום shalom shalom right it
is all very much around תורה and תורה sages and as Michael
points out it's למען בית השם אלוקינו, lema'an beit Hashem Elokeinu, but
a בית השם אלוקינו beit Hashem Elokeinu was like just the normal
progression from talking about תלמידי חכמים מרבים שלום בעולם talmidei chachamim marbim
shalom ba'olam so really does seem that it's a fascinating that the
end of the מסכת masechet whereas in the משנה mishna the end
sort of seemed to be ברכות and greeting people with God's name
and that sort of use of God in the day-to-day is the
way we have קדושה kedusha post מקדש. The end of the גמרא
Gemara not surprisingly seems to be that תורה becomes the יבנה is
the replacement of the מקדש and through being עוסק בתורה osek baTorah
is how one really sort of encounters God בציון beTzion and has
those מקדש type of experiences and has a center of קדושה kedusha
even in our case and with that הדרן עלך ברכות וסליקא לך
מסכת. hadran alach Berachot uslika lach masechet.